Guide to the West Indian Carnival Documentation Project records 2010.019
Brooklyn Historical Society
The West Indian Carnival Documentation Project records
1993-1996
1994-1995
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
2010.019
28 Gigabytes in 288 files, total running time: 30 hours, 15 minutes, 57 seconds; 5.0 linear feet in 9 boxes
This collection includes research materials, oral histories, and photographs collected through the West Indian Carnival Documentation Project, undertaken by Brooklyn Historical Society in the mid-1990s. The project attempted to supplement existing scholarship with oral histories done with members of the West Indian community and Carnival participants.
Historical Note
The West Indian Carnival tradition in New York City stems from private gatherings and parties held in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan in the 1920s, typically in February. In the 1940s, an outdoor street festival began taking place on 7th Avenue in Harlem, organized by Trinidadian Jessie Wattle. In 1967, the Carnival was moved to Eastern Parkway in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn following a disturbance that led to its street permit being revoked in Manhattan. At this same time, the West Indian American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA) was founded. The Association was run by Trinidadian Carlos Lezama from 1967 until 2001, and was later headed by his daughter, Yolanda Lezama-Clark. With Thomas Bailey serving as President since 2012, the West Indian Carnival in Brooklyn is now one of the largest outdoor street festivals in North America.
Carnival activities begin on the Thursday before Labor Day and continue through Monday, concluding with the parade itself. Other events and activities include a steel band competition and a Kiddie Carnival. The parade itself takes months of preparation from each masquerade camp or "mas," which designs its own elaborate and colorful costumes around a central theme and competes for prizes with the other camps. Parade participants are accompanied by various musical groups and styles, as well as food vendors, brought together to celebrate pan-Caribbean culture.
The Brooklyn Historical Society launched The West Indian Carnival Documentation Project in 1994 in cooperation with the West Indian American Day Carnival Association and the Brooklyn Museum with a goal of supplementing existing photographs and histories of the event with personal narratives and life histories of Carnival participants. Those involved with the project attempted to get different viewpoints within the hierarchy of Carnival organization and participation. The oral histories, photographs and resources that make up this collection were compiled by a team including two community researchers, photographers from local Caribbean publications, graduate student assistants, scholarly advisors and a community advisory committee primarily made up of WIADCA members. Staff for this project included Dwandalyn Reece King (Chief Curator), Michael Roberts (Interviewer), Joyce Quamina (Research Assistant), Megan McShea (Project Assistant), Maureen Mahon (Project Fieldworker) and Kristen Elmquist (Project Fieldworker).
Arrangement
The West Indian Carnival Documentation Project records were largely kept in their original order. Series were formed based on format. The oral history transcripts, tapes, and digitized audio are arranged alphabetically. Each folder of photographs represents one reel of film and the photos remain in the order in which they were taken and developed. The folders are organized chronologically. The research materials are located in three boxes, the third of which contains oversized materials. The first two boxes are arranged alphabetically.
The collection is organized into the following four series. Series 1: Oral histories consists of digitized oral history interview recordings of most of the interviews. Series 2: Oral history transcripts includes transcripts and cassette tapes of most of the interviews. The interview with Wesley Millington does not have a transcript. The Debra Holland interview was not preserved. Interview abstracts are located in the "Summaries" folder in box 2.
Many of the topics and people discussed in the oral history interviews are also represented in Series 3: Photographs. When available, these are included in the folder title as well as the series scope and content note. The photos document the Parade itself, in addition to the organizers and participants, costumes, music, instruments, rehearsals and Carnival preparation in general. Though the majority of the series is made up of 4 x 6 color prints, there are also some corresponding negatives, contact sheets, and a few larger prints.
Series 4: Research materials is made from what was gathered and generated through the documentation project. The materials relate directly to the West Indian Carnival in Brooklyn, as well as to Carnivals in London and Trinidad. They also describe the pan-Caribbean community in and outside of Brooklyn. This series includes magazines, newspapers, pamphlets, articles, bibliographies and resource lists, and ephemeral materials.
Oral History note
Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between two people, both of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Brooklyn Historical Society archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that:
1. The Brooklyn Historical Society abides by the General Principles & Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics.
2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access whenever possible, BHS presents these views as recorded.
3. Transcripts created prior to 2008 serve as a guide to the interview and are not considered verbatim. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, repetitions that are common in conversation, and other passages and phrases omitted from the transcript. This decision was made because BHS gives primacy to the audible voice and also because some researchers do find useful information in these verbal patterns.
4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator's speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers with varied restrictions according to narrator agreement. Oral histories can be accessed onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal. Exhibition research materials are open to researchers upon request and are accessible onsite at the Othmer Library.
Related Archival Materials
In addition to this collection, Brooklyn Historical Society has oral history collections and other records related to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn.
- The Crown Heights History Project collection includes thirty-three interviews conducted from 1993 to 1994. (1994.006)
- The Listen to this: Crown Heights Oral History collection includes forty-three interviews conducted in 2010 (2010.020)
- Eastern Parkway Coalition records, 1952-2007 (2007.016)
- 959 Park Place Tenants' Association records (1978.009)
For more information on these collections please visit our online finding aid portal.
Related collections located elsewhere include:
- The Daphne Weeks Collection, 1993-1994 at the New York Public Library (Sc MG 741)
- Institutional files related to the West Indian American Day Carnival Association at the Brooklyn Museum of Art
Separated Materials
Personal documents relating to the documentation project team and hiring process were separated from the collection and added to the administrative files at Brooklyn Historical Society.
Scope and Contents
The West Indian Carnival Documentation Project records include photographs, oral histories (audio and transcripts), publications and research, and ephemeral materials relating to the Carnival and the project itself. The materials were collected and created within the context of a documentation project undertaken by the Brooklyn Historical Society in 1994, which later culminated in an exhibition. Exhibition materials are not included in the collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The oral histories, photographs, and resources that make up this collection were compiled by a team including two community researchers, photographers from local Caribbean publications, graduate student assistants, scholarly advisors and a community advisory committee primarily made up of WIADCA members. Staff for this project included Dwandalyn Reece King (Chief Curator), Michael Roberts (Interviewer), Joyce Quamina (Research Assistant), Megan McShea (Project Assistant), Maureen Mahon (Project Fieldworker) and Kristen Elmquist (Project Fieldworker). Most recordings and transcripts were digitized in 2011.
African Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Articles; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); London (England); Oral histories (document genres); Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Photographs; Records (documents); Trinidad; West Indian Americans; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Oral Histories, 28 Gigabytes in 288 files
  - Adams, Val, 1994 September 24; 2010.019.01
    Biographical / Historical
    Val Adams was born in St. Patrick's, Grenada in 1956. Raised in a musical family, he began performing at an early age and achieved local success in his teens. He immigrated to Brooklyn in 1974 at age eighteen. He continued in music, forming his own group, which became a fixture at Grenadian functions in New York City. Adams was instrumental in increasing Grenadian participation in Eastern Parkway festivities.
    Scope and Contents
    In the interview, Val Adams discusses his musical beginnings and his participation in Carnival in Grenada with particular reference to local mas genres, Jab Jab and Shortknee. He discusses his early impressions of Brooklyn and talks at some length about his continued musical career in New York. He discusses his involvement with the Carnival on Eastern Parkway and his attempts to increase Grenadian participation despite some resistance. Adams describes his impressions of the Brooklyn Carnival as a unique expression of pan-Caribbean unity and African American culture. Adams compares regional differences in Carnival traditions, how the Brooklyn Carnival has changed over time, the economic benefits and some of the challenges facing the celebration. Interview conducted by Michael Roberts.
    Conditions Governing Access and Use
    Access to the interview is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal. Use of the oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires the permission of BHS. For assistance, contact library@brooklynhistory.org.
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Boston (Mass.); Brazil; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Economic conditions; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Jamaica; Grenadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Grenadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Saint Vincent and the Grenadines; Toronto (Ont.); Trinidad; Trinidadian Americans |z United States; Washington (D.C.); Adams, Val; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Adolphus, Jeffrey, 1994 August 26; 2010.019.02
    Jeffrey Adolphus (born circa 1952 - ) was born in Belize. He immigrated to Brooklyn after high school in 1971 and formed a band, playing keyboards as a full-time musician. He completed a five-year music program, worked for United Airlines, Wells Fargo, the Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA), and finally, the Board of Education. Adolphus was instrumental in getting New York's Belizeans officially involved in the West Indian Carnival parade in 1991 through his organization, the Belizean Carnival and Recreational Association (BECRA).
    In the interview, Jeffrey Adolphus discusses his initial impressions of Brooklyn and his early efforts to gain Belizean entry into the West Indian Carnival parade. He contrasts Belizean, New Yorker, and Trinidadian attitudes toward the parade and describes the role of New York and Miami Belizeans in reinvigorating the Carnival tradition in Belize. Adolphus describes his personal connection to the parade and the depth of his commitment with detailed discussions of selecting themes and designing costumes. He describes Belizean culture's mélange of ethnic traditions with an only recently popularized musical tradition and emphasizes the parade's importance in promoting and disseminating Belizean culture and identity. Adolphus discusses fundraising, the challenges involved in organizing a parade contingent, and changes he'd like to see; including the importance of reaching out to the general African American community. He feels that the group doesn't necessarily see themselves reflected in the parade, which is a partial cause of resentment and violence. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Belize; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Central Americans |z Belize; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Musicians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Adolphus, Jeffrey; Belizean Carnival and Recreational Association (BECRA); West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Alexander, Jean, 1994 June 27; 2010.019.03
    Jean Alexander was born and raised in St. Joseph, Trinidad. She is of East Indian descent. Married at fifteen, she traveled with her husband and children twice to the United States in 1963 and 1968 before permanently immigrating in 1971. The family moved to Brooklyn in 1975. Alexander is a long-standing member of the West Indian American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA) and was the public relations officer for the Caribbean-American Center.
    In the interview, Jean Alexander discusses the role that class played in how one participated in Carnival in Trinidad. Introduced to the West Indian American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA) in 1974, she soon became involved in the organization as its public relations director, a position she still held in 1994 at the time of the interview. She reflects on the experience of Carnival and considers the economic resources the Carnival annually brings to New York City. She notes that the contributions of the Caribbean community have not been fully acknowledged by the government or the media. Alexander suggests that WIADCA should be a year round institution that can serve the community; providing resources for job training and employment and addressing the need of the organization to involve more people from other Caribbean islands. She also discusses the cultural conflicts that have occurred among organizers and finishes with a description of the activities and services provided by the non-profit Caribbean-American Center, of which WIADCA was an affiliate. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Trinidadians |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Economic conditions; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Washington (D.C.); Toronto (Ont.); Trinidad; Trinidadian Americans |z United States; Alexander, Jean; Lezama, Carlos; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Alexander, Kendell, 1994 July 29; 2010.019.04
    Access to this recording is restricted by the donor. Please contact library@brooklynhistory.org for further questions.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Alexander, Kendell
  - Brewster, Randy, 1994 August 18; 2010.019.05
    Randy Brewster was born in Trinidad and came to New York in 1961. His first involvement in Carnival in Trinidad was playing "Indian." He was a founder of the Culture of Black Creation, a costume design and production shop serving New York, Westchester and Trinidad. His partner/designer is Francis "Jackie" Clavery. At the time of the interview in 1994, he worked as a dental technician.
    In the interview, Randy Brewster recalls his early involvement with Carnival in Trinidad. He discusses developing carnival themes and the intrigue involved in keeping them secret with some elaboration on the judging criteria in Trinidad versus Brooklyn. He then describes the process of sketching and design in conjunction with his production partner, Jackie Clavery, and they discuss the hierarchy of carnival competition. Brewster discusses what Carnival means to him and regrets the lack of costume preservation. He describes the scope and logistics of the production process and discusses both positive and negative aspects of the Brooklyn parade; including the difference between a parade and a carnival or street festival (gumbi). He notes the emphasis on novelty each year and the pleasure he gets from watching youth involvement in the Kiddies Carnival, including that of his own children. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Art |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Canada; Carnival; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Costume designers |z Trinidad; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Trinidad; Brewster, Randy; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Brewster, Winston, 1995 March 28; 2010.019.06
    Winston Brewster was born in San Fernando, Trinidad. In 1969, at the age of thirty, he immigrated to the United States. Brewster first lived in Queens, where his family was located. He then moved to Brooklyn, where he still resided at the time of this interview, in 1995. While he participated in mas in Trinidad, he did not participate in Brooklyn, New York. Instead, Brewster was involved as a vendor of Trinidadian food. When not preparing to sell food at his two stalls, he worked as a welder.
    In this interview Winston Brewster discusses his involvement as a food vendor at Brooklyn's West Indian Carnival. He reflects on the early days of the Carnival in the late 1960s; noting the changes in the route, number of spectators, and how the structure of food vending has evolved. He also notes the Brooklyn Carnival's parallels to the Trinidadian Carnival. Brewster discusses the impact of the Carnival on the Caribbean community and the wider New York community; noting the presence of a growing multicultural participation. He considers the Carnival's enormity and suggests that the cultural presence can and has influenced the city's political decisions. The specific example provided concerned a controversy in 1994 when the onset of the Jewish holy day Rosh Hashanah coincided with Carnival. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Economic conditions; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Street vendors |z New York (State) |z New York; Trinidad; Trinidadian Americans |z United States; Brewster, Winston; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Byron, Cheryl, 1994 September 29; 2010.019.07
    Cheryl Byron was born on the island of Trinidad. In 1974, she immigrated to New York. She received her bachelor's and master's degrees, in English, from City College, City University of New York. At the time of the interview in 1994, Byron was teaching at Medgar Evers College, Fort Greene Senior Citizens Center, and John Houseman Berean Church; all located in Brooklyn, where she had recently moved. Enrolled in a doctoral program at New York University, she was completing a dissertation with the working title, "Brooklyn Carnival: Theater and Art." A prolific painter, Cheryl Byron was the first poet to perform in the calypso tent at the West Indian American Day Carnival. An old mas enthusiast and founder of the performing arts company Something Positive, Inc., her artistic contributions continuously enriched Brooklyn's Carnival. Cheryl Byron died of cancer in 2003.